Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub Made possible with a grant from the Leon Levy Foundation 2009-2011 MSS 309
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
- Tom Colicchio
  Bras, Michel; Bryan, Jerry; Colicchio & Sons (Restaurant).; Colicchio, Tom; Craft (Restaurant).; Food Research and Action Center.; Gramercy Tavern.; Keller, Thomas, 1955-; Meyer, Danny; Mondrian (Restaurant).; Portale, Alfred; Silverbush, Lori; Top Chef (Television Program).; Wine, Barry; Cooking; Dinners and dining; Gastronomy.; Local foods; Nutrition; Restaurant management; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; School children |x Food; Television cooking shows
  - Interview 1, April 19, 2011
  - Interview 2, May 12, 2011
- Mark Federman
  - Interview 1, January 25, 2011
  - Interview 2, January 31, 2011
- John Ferrone
  John Ferrone was already a respected New York literary editor when he met James Beard and the two became lifelong friends. That friendship took Ferrone beyond his already illustrious list of authors—Anais Nin, Alice Walker, Eudora Welty, C.S. Lewis, Janet Flanner—into the world of food.
  Working at night after he finished his day job, Ferrone began, out of a devotion to the friendship, editing scores of Beard's articles. Eventually he worked on some of Beard's books and continued to do so (as Beard’s literary executor) after his death. The books include: the James Beard Cookbook, the Armchair James Beard, and several small format books, including: Soups and Stews and Poultry and Shellfish. Ferrone continues to steward Beard's books and attempt keep them in print.
  Ferrone discusses not only he and Beard's friendship and their work together, but also others in Beard's circle. He also speaks of their many meals together. A list of those meals, compiled by Ferrone, is included in this file.
  Brown, Helen Evans
  Callvert, Isabel E.
  Cofacci, Gino
  Coward, Noel, 1899-1973
  Ferrone, John
  Flanner, Janet, 1892-1978
  Sax, Irene
  Triplette, Clay
  Walker, Alice, 1944-
  Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001
  Wilson, José
  Dell Publishing Company
  Green Giant Company
  Harcourt, Inc.
  Authors and publishers
  Food writers
  Homosexuality
  Manuscript preparation (Authorship)
  Manuscripts -- Editing
  Beard, James, 1903-1985; Brown, Helen Evans; Callvert, Isabel E.; Claiborne, Craig; Cofacci, Gino; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973; Dell Publishing Company.; Ferrone, John; Flanner, Janet, 1892-1978; Green Giant Company.; Harcourt, Inc..; Sax, Irene; Triplette, Clay; Walker, Alice, 1944-; Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001; Wilson, José; Authors and publishers.; Cookbooks.; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Dinners and dining; Entertaining; Food Writers; Gastronomy.; Homosexuality; Manuscript preparation (Authorship); Manuscripts |x Editing; Menus.; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, March 3, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 36 minutes
  - Interview 2, March 5, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 6 minutes
  - Interview 3, April 1, 2010
    Running time: 53 minutes
- Betty Fussell
  The distinguished historian Betty Fussell was one of the first American writers to focus on food as a legitimate subject of scientific, social, and anthropological inquiry.
  In her 1999, The Story of Corn: the Myths and History, the Culture and Agriculture, the Art and Science of America's Quintessential Crop, Fussel used the history of corn to tell a distinctly American story. She also created a genre, now much imitated by other writers, focused on a single foodstuff.
  Born in 1927 in California and reared there, she has made her home in New York's Greenwich Village for decades. She lives around the corner from James Beard's cooking school run out of his home. Her only contact was a week's worth of classes there, but they share an abiding passion for American food.
  Her essays in literary journals, major newspapers, national magazines and encyclopedias are written with a grace few food writers can match. She also lectures at museums, universities, state fairs, corn festivals, historical societies and culinary groups. In 1999, her food memoir, My Kitchen Wars, traced her life from her childhoood through her marriage to a college sweetheart, her travails as an academic wife, her own academic career, the women's movement, and her wider success when she found her essential subject: food.
  Fussell discusses her early years as well as her life and work since 1999, including her presence in the growing food blogosphere.
  Bocuse, Paul, 1926-
  Child, Julia
  David, Elizabeth, 1913-1992
  Fisher, M. F. K. (Mary Frances Kennedy), 1908-1992
  Fussell, Betty Harper
  Fussell, Paul, 1924-
  Jones, Judith, 1924-
  Hodgson, Moira
  Normand, Mabel, 1894-1930
  Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.
  American Institute of Wine & Food
  Doubleday and Company, Inc.
  International Association of Culinary Professionals
  Ordre international des disciples d'Auguste Escoffier
  Ticknor and Fields
  Times Books (New York, N.Y.)
  Viking Press
  Blogs
  Cooking, American -- Midwestern style
  Cooking, French
  Cooking -- Study and teaching
  Corn
  Food habits
  Marriage
  Sex roles
  Universities and colleges -- Faculty
  Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.; American Institute of Wine & Food.; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Bocuse, Paul, 1926-; Child, Julia; Claiborne, Craig; David, Elizabeth, 1913-1992; Doubleday and Company, Inc..; Fisher, M. F. K., (Mary Frances Kennedy), 1908-1992; Fussell, Betty Harper; Fussell, Paul, 1924-; Hodhson, Moira; International Association of Culinary Professionals.; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Normand, Mabel, 1894-1930; Ordre international des disciples d'Auguste Escoffier.; Ticknor and Fields.; Times Books (New York, N.Y.).; Viking Press.; Authors and publishers.; Authorship; Blogs; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, American |x Midwestern style; Cooking, French; Corn; Dinners and dining; Entertaining; Feminism.; Food habits; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Marriage; Menus.; Sex roles; Universities and colleges |x Faculty
  - Interview 1, March 24, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 39 minutes
  - Interview 2, May 18, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour
  - Interview 3, May 20, 2010
    Running time: 37 minutes
- Gael Greene
  Gael Greene, the New York Magazine restaurant critic, knew James Beard casually when an article in The New York Times brought them together. The piece described the plight of impoverished senior citizens who received food aid from the city during the week, but had no source of food on weekends and holidays.
  The situation appalled her, and she was inspired to call everyone she could think of who might have money or goods to ameliorate the situation.
  James Beard was one of those people. It was common knowledge that food companies often sent Beard samples of their products in the hope that he would try them, like them, and, with luck, promote them in his columns. Greene figured Beard might have some actual food to contribute on a more-or-less regular basis.
  Jumping into action, she phoned him to enlist his support, and encouraged him to join her effort to remedy the situation. The result was CityMeals On Wheels, where he lent his name and enthusiasm to a project that still exists today.
  Greene left New York Magazine in 2008 and today has become an active free-lance writer, blogger, and tweeter. Her interview discusses the inception of CityMeals on Wheels as well as her early years as a free-lance writer and book author, and her early work at New York Magazine.
  Felker, Clay
  Forgione, Larry
  Frieman, Jane
  Greene, Gael
  Kretchmer, Jerry
  Portali, Alfred
  Soltner, André, 1932-
  Waxman, Jonathan. 1950-
  Meals on Wheels
  New York Magazine
  New York Post
  Time, Inc.
  Benefit auctions
  Cooking – Study and teaching
  Journalism
  Restaurants -- New York (State) - - New York
  Beard, James, 1903-1985; Claiborne, Craig; Felker, Clay; Forgione, Larry; Frieman, Jane; Greene, Gael; Kretchmer, Jerry; Meals on Wheels.; New York Magazine.; New York Post.; Portale, Alfred; Soltner, André, 1932-; Time, Inc..; Waxman, Jonathan, 1950-; Authorship; Benefit auctions; Cooking |v Periodicals; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Dinners and dining; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Journalism.; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, June 19, 2010
    Running Time: 53 minutes
- Dan Imhoff
  The first decade of the 21st century has been marked by an increasing concern about flaws and dangers in the American food system, a world dominated by the rules and regulations of the United States Farm Bills. Massive and abstruse pieces of federal legislation that are reworked every five years or so, the farm bills are little understood but enormously influential on food and farm related subjects from food stamps to commodity crops to conservation and trade.
  Activist speaker, writer and publisher Dan Imhoff illuminated that world for the lay public (and perhaps also for members of Congress) in his 2007 book, Food Fight: The Citizen's Guide to a Food and Farm Bill.
  This Interview tracks over Imhoff's childhood in York PA, his education, his travels in Asia and Europe after college, some of important influences in his thinking about the environment (including a businessman who later became his father-in-law), his interest in a variety of environmental issues, and his life in Northern California, where he and his wife have a small farm that provides much of the food for their family.
  With the recent publication of CAFO: The Tragedy of Industrial Animal Factories, Imhoff took on the increasingly contentious world of American meat production. He is currently at work on a revised edition of Food Fight.
  Imhoff, Dan
  Imhoff, Quincey Tompkins
  Jackson, Wes
  Kirschenmann, Fred
  Tompkins, Douglas
  Esprit (Firm)
  Foundation for Deep Ecology
  Kellogg Foundation
  Watershed Media
  Wild Farm Alliance
  Agricultural processing industry
  Agricultural subsidies -- Law and legislation
  Agriculture and state
  Animal rights
  Environmentalism
  Factory farms
  Food stamps
  Esprit (Firm).; Foundation for Deep Ecology.; Imhoff, Dan; Imhoff, Quincey Tompkins; Jackson, Wes; Kellogg Foundation.; Kirschenmann, Fred; Tompkins, Douglas; Watershed Media.; Wild Farm Alliance.; Agricultural processing industries; Agricultural subsidies |x Law and legislation; Agriculture and state; Animal rights; Authorship; Community -supported agriculture; Environmentalism; Factory farms; Food industry and trade; Food stamps; Nutrition
  - Interview 1, April 14, 2011
- Madhur Jaffrey
  Few American cooks were able to produce authentic Indian food until Madhur Jaffrey's 1973 An Introduction to Indian Cooking. The book demystified Indian food and in a way, was a reflection of her own introduction to Indian cooking, once she left New Delhi to pursue an acting career in England and America. Like many upper class Indian women, Jaffrey hadn't learned to cook as a child. Once she left home, she longed for the food of her childhood. Letters from her mother as well as Jaffrey's own strong sense of taste set her on her way.
  A well-known Indian actress, Jaffrey was at home in front of cameras and. As her food writing career developed, that experience made her a natural for television. Since that first cookbook—then praised by New York Times food critic Craig Claiborne as "perhaps the best Indian cookbook available in English"—she has written 28 more, many of them in tandem with multiple television series both in the United States and the UK. She has also written countless newspaper and magazine articles, and continued a much-praised acting career. Both of those threads of her life are discussed in this interview.
  Allen, Sanford
  Ivory, James
  Jhabvala, Ruth Prawer, 1927-
  Jaffrey, Madhur, 1933-
  Jaffrey, Saeed, 1929-
  Merchant, Ismail
  British Broadcasting Corporation
  Merchant Ivory Productions
  Acting
  Cooking, Indic
  India -- History -- 1947-
  Motion pictures
  Theater
  Vegetarian cooking
  Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.; Allen, Sanford; Beard, James, 1903-1985; British Broadcasting Corporation.; Claiborne, Craig; Gourmet.; Ivory, James; Jaffrey, Madhur, 1933-; Jaffrey, Saeed, 1929-; Jhabvaka, Ruth Prawer, 1927-; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Merchant Ivory Productions.; Merchant, Ismail; Acting.; Authorship; Cookbooks.; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, Indic; Dinners and dining; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; India |x History |y 1947-; Motion pictures.; Publishers and publishing; Television cooking shows; Theater.; Vegetarian cooking
  - Interview 1, December 2, 2010
  - Interview 2, December 16, 2010
- Judith Jones
  Judith Jones first made her mark in publishing as a young woman working in the Paris office of Doubleday, when she came upon a manuscript of The Diary of Anne Frank in a reject pile and enthusiastically recommended it for publication. That star turn gave her considerable credibility when, back in the United States working as an editor for Knopf, she urged the publishing house to pay attention to an unsolicited manuscript by Julia Child, Louisette Bertholle, and Simone Beck that would become Mastering the Art of French Cooking.
  A prominent fiction editor already, Jones went on to discover and edit not only the rest of Julia Child's books, but also books by some of the most successful cookbook authors in America, including Madhur Jaffrey, Marcella Hazan, Irene Kuo, Edna Lewis, and Joan Nathan. More than any other figure in publishing, she has helped to change the way America thinks about food. She has also authored books, both with her late husband Evan Jones and on her own. In 2006, she received a Lifetime Achievement Award from the James Beard Foundation.
  Chapin, Paul
  Cunningham, Marion
  Farmer, Fannie Merritt, 1857-1915
  Frank, Anne, 1929-1945
  Giobbi, Edward
  Jones, Evan, 1915-1996
  Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984
  Knopf, Blanche W., 1894-1966
  Kuo, Irene
  Lewis, Edna
  Malraux, André, 1901-1976
  Pépin, Jacques
  Roden, Claudia
  Updike, John
  Weil, Andrew
  Bread
  Diet
  Editing
  Restaurants --- New York (State) -- New York
  Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.; Bastianich, Lidia; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Chapin, Paul; Child, Julia; Cunningham, Marion; David, Elizabeth, 1913-1992; Doubleday and Company, Inc..; Farmer, Fannie Merritt, 1857-1915; Frank, Anne, 1929-1945; Giobbi, Edward; Jaffrey, Madhur, 1933-; Jones, Evan, 1915-1996; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984; Knopf, Blanche W., 1894-1966; Kuo, Irene; Lewis, Edna; Malraux, André, 1901-1976; Pépin, Jacques; Roden, Claudia; Updike, John; Weil, Andrew; Wilson, José; Authors and publishers.; Bread; Cookbooks.; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, French; Diet; Dinners and dining; Editing; Food habits; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Manuscripts |x Editing; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, April 27, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 22 minutes
  - Interview 2, May 7, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 9 minutes
- Barbara Kafka, Dial Publishing Company.
  An acclaimed presence in the food world for decades, Barbara Kafka has been a cookbook author, food writer, and a food and restaurant consultant.
  No other writer working today can claim as long a professional association with James Beard. Their association began when she was hired to supervise and write much of The Cook's Catalogue, a book edited by Beard with Milton Glaser and Burton Richard Wolf in 1975. She continued to work with him, teaching classes at his cooking schools in California and New York, and helping him with his writing. After Beard's death, she put together The James Beard's Celebration Cookbook in order to raise money for the James Beard Foundation. Kafka's own exhaustively-researched single-subject cookbooks ( Vegetables, Roasting, Microwave Cooking) have set a standard for excellence. In 2007, Kafka received a Lifetime Achievement Award from the James Beard Foundation.
  In her interview, she discusses her relationship with Beard and her own extensive work.
  Bramson, Ann
  Cage, John
  Cournand, Edouard
  Ferrrone, John
  Glaser, Milton
  Guerin, Jacques
  Kafka, Barbara
  Kump, Peter
  Talmey, Allene
  Tower, Jeremiah
  Villas, James
  Wolf, Burton
  Dial Publishing Company
  Farrar, Straus, and Company
  Mademoiselle
  Playbill
  Revue du vin de France
  Vogue
  Celiac disease
  Cooking -- Equipment and supplies
  Microwave cooking
  Wine
  Baum, Joseph; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Bramson, Ann; Cage, John; Child, Julia; Cofacci, Gino; Cournand, Edouard; Cunningham, Marion; Farrar, Straus, and Company.; Ferrone, John; Four Seasons (Restaurant).; Glaser, Milton; Guerin, Jacques; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Kafka, Barbara; Kump, Peter; Mademoiselle.; Playbill.; Revue du vin de France.; Sax, Irene; Talmey, Allene; Tower, Jeremiah; Villas, James; Vogue.; Waters, Alice; Wilson, José; Windows on the World (New York, N.Y.).; Wolf, Burton; Authorship; Celiac disease; Cookbooks.; Cooking |v Periodicals; Cooking |x Equipment and supplies; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, French; Food writing.; Homosexuality; Journalism.; Microwave cooking; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Wine
  - Interview 1, April 3, 2010
    Running time: 2 hours, 9 minutes
  - Interview 2, April 6, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 35 minutes
  - Interview 3, April 13, 2010
- Marion Nestle
  Marion Nestle is the premiere food studies professional in the United States. She unequivocally transformed the field when, in 1988, she took over the Department of Home Economics and Nutrition at New York University, and soon turned it into a ground-breaking academic program in nutrition, food studies, and public health.
  Her path traces a childhood without much parental encouragement, academic successes and multiple degrees, a pre-second wave feminism early career filled with the common restrictions and frustrations women then faced, and an adulthood at the highest rank of academic and personal achievement.
  A much sought-after speaker with particular interests in food politics, food marketing, and nutrition, she has written five books, and balances a schedule that includes teaching; research and writing; speaking; and an active highly-read blog (www.foodpolitics.com).
  This interview covers her early life and education; her two marriages; the challenges of balancing motherhood and a career; the responsibilities and challenges she faced writing the 1988 Surgeon General's Report on Nutrition and Health; her books; her years at New York University; and the development of the University’s Food Studies Department.
  Bentley, Amy, 1962-
  Berg, Jennifer
  Brody, Jane E.
  Burros, Marian Fox
  Gussow, Joan Dye
  Koop, C. Everett (Charles Everett), 1916-
  Lee, Philip R.
  McGinnis, Michael
  Petrick, Gabriella M.
  Pollan, Michael
  Ray, Krishnendu
  Wolf, Clark
  American Dietetic Association
  Brandeis University
  Dames d'Escoffier of New York
  Monsanto Agricultural Company
  New York Times
  New York University
  Newsweek
  United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services
  United States. Dept. of Agriculture
  University of California, Berkeley
  University of California School of Medicine, San Francisco
  Children -- Nutrition
  Farm produce -- Marketing -- Government policy
  Food adulteration and inspection
  Food security
  Junk food
  Health
  Pet food industry
  Public health
  Urban agriculture
  Women in higher education
  American Dietetic Association.; Bentley, Amy, 1962-; Berg, Jennifer; Brandeis University.; Brody, Jane E.; Burros, Marian Fox; Dames d'Escoffier of New York.; Fales Library.; Gussow, Joan Dye; Koop, C. Everett, (Charles Everett), 1916-; Lee, Philip R.; McGinnis, Michael; Monsanto Agricultural Company.; Nestle, Marion; New York Times.; New York University.; Newsweek.; Petrick, Gabriella M.; Pollan, Michael; Ray, Krishnendu; Taylor, Marvin J.; United States. Department of Agriculture.; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services.; University of California School of Medicine, San Francisco.; University of California, Berkeley.; Wolf, Clark; Agricultural processing industries; Agriculture and state; Authorship; Children |x Nutrition; Diet; Editing; Farm produce |x Marketing |x Government policy; Feminism.; Food adulteration and inspection; Food industry and trade; Food security; Health; Junk food; Nutrition; Pet food industry; Public health; Sex roles; Urban agriculture; Women in higher education
  - Interview 1, May 19, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 48 minutes
  - Interview 2, May 26, 2010
    Running time: 45 minutes
  - Interview 3, June 29, 2010
    Running time: 56 minutes
- Jacques Pepin
  Long before cable reality programs brought chefs into American homes, Jacques Pepin was already there, starring in his own multiple cooking series on public television.
  Pepin's father was a cabinetmaker and his mother ran a restaurant. When his family sent him out as a restaurant apprentice, their goal was both to feed him and to teach him a trade. He discovered a passion for the work and his talent soon propelled him from the provinces, to the kitchens of French presidents, to one of New York's best restaurants. When a serious automobile accident made long hours in a restaurant impossible, he turned to teaching and then television.
  Along the way he became a husband and father, an American citizen, a bestselling writer, and one of the guiding spirits of both the prestigious French Culinary Institute in Manhattan and the culinary program at Boston University.
  Included among his more than 20 books are arguably two of the most influential on cooking techniques ever written in this country, La Technique and La Methode. His eleven television series, with more on the way, have reflected both his years in America and a wide range of culinary possibilities, from cooking for celebrations to cooking with Julia Child.
  Curnonsky, 1872-1956
  Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970
  Gaulle, Yvonne de, 1900-1979
  Franey, Pierre
  McCully, Helen
  Boston University
  French Culinary Institute (New York, N.Y.)
  Howard Johnson Co.
  Pavillon (Restaurant: New York, N.Y.)
  Plaza Athénée
  Société Des Cuisiniers
  Restaurants -- France -- Paris
  Beard, James, 1903-1985; Boston University.; Child, Julia; Claiborne, Craig; Curnonsky, 1872-1956; Franey, Pierre; French Culinary Institute (New York, N.Y.).; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970; Gaulle, Yvonne de, 1900-1979; Howard Johnson Co..; McCully, Helen; New York Times.; Pavillon (Restaurant: New York, N.Y.).; Plaza Athénée.; Pépin, Jacques; Société Des Cuisiniers.; Authorship; Cookbooks.; Cooking |v Periodicals; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, French; Dinners and dining; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z France |z Paris; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Television cooking shows
  - Interview 1, November 10, 2009
    Running time: 2 hours, 28 minutes
- Irene Sax
  A journalist and food writer, Irene Sax co-wrote Beard on Pasta and helped him prepare magazine articles. She became the food editor of New York Newsday, which closed in 1995, and now teaches food writing at New York University, while maintaining an active career as a freelance food writer and occasional restaurant critic.
  Sax discusses her working relationship with Beard and other aspects of her career.
  Jones, Judith, 1924 -
  Disney.com
  Epicurious
  Martha Stewart Living
  New York Daily News
  Newsday
  Freelance writing
  Ghostwriting